<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The banner of Gods love, and ensign of righteousness spread over his people in these later dayes. Wherein the true light shineth, and the mysterie that hath been hid from ages and generations, is revealed to the saints, which is, Christ in us the hope of glory, as our forefathers witnessed, read Col. I. 26, 27, 28, 29. Also, a testimony against them who formerly hath tasted of the good word of God, and of the power of the world to come, who hath cast the law of God behind their backs, and hath trodden under foot the blood of the covenant. ... most especially, those that are called Anabaptists and Independents. Also, a few words in warning to the priests, professors, and people of the town and county of Southhampton. With a few quæries to the rulers and magistrates of England, to try their fruits whether they be according to the Christian magistrates recorded in the Scripture of truth, ... . Set forth most especially for the sake of the honest-hearted, who are not wholly given up to believe lyes, that they may come to know the way of life and peace. Written by me who are called Ambrose Rigge.</title>
            <author>Rigge, Ambrose, 1635?-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91825</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E932_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22061</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871571</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871571</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168503</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91825)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168503)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 140:E932[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The banner of Gods love, and ensign of righteousness spread over his people in these later dayes. Wherein the true light shineth, and the mysterie that hath been hid from ages and generations, is revealed to the saints, which is, Christ in us the hope of glory, as our forefathers witnessed, read Col. I. 26, 27, 28, 29. Also, a testimony against them who formerly hath tasted of the good word of God, and of the power of the world to come, who hath cast the law of God behind their backs, and hath trodden under foot the blood of the covenant. ... most especially, those that are called Anabaptists and Independents. Also, a few words in warning to the priests, professors, and people of the town and county of Southhampton. With a few quæries to the rulers and magistrates of England, to try their fruits whether they be according to the Christian magistrates recorded in the Scripture of truth, ... . Set forth most especially for the sake of the honest-hearted, who are not wholly given up to believe lyes, that they may come to know the way of life and peace. Written by me who are called Ambrose Rigge.</title>
                  <author>Rigge, Ambrose, 1635?-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at his shop at the Black spread-Eagle, neer the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Bodleian Library (Early English books) and in the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168503:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BANNER OF GODS LOVE, AND ENSIGN OF RIGHTEOVSNESS <hi>Spread over his people in theſe later dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the true light ſhineth, and the myſterie that hath been hid from Ages and Generations, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to the Saints, which is, <hi>Chriſt in us the hope of glory,</hi> as our forefathers witneſſed, Read <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 26, 27, 28, 29.</p>
            <p>ALSO, A Teſtimony againſt them who formerly hath taſted of the good Word of God, and of the Power of the world to come, who hath caſt the Law of God behind their backs, and hath trodden under foot the blood of the Covenant, and now doth labour with one ſhoulder to deſtroy the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child which is now brought forth to rule the Nations with an Iron Rod; and theſe are moſt eſpecially, thoſe that are called <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Independents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo, A few Words in warning to the Prieſts, Profeſſors, and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Town and County of <hi>Southampton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a few <hi>Quaeries</hi> to the Rulers and Magiſtrates of <hi>England,</hi> to try their fruits whether they be according to the Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates recorded in the Scripture of truth, or according to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Kings and Rulers in former Ages.</p>
            <p>Set forth moſt eſpecially for the ſake of the honeſt-hearted, who are not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given up to believe lyes, that they may come to know the way of life and peace. Written by me who am called <hi>Ambroſe Rigge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the <hi>Black ſpread-Eagle,</hi> neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168503:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168503:2"/>
            <head>To the ſober Reader.</head>
            <p>GReat and admirable is the Love and Mercy of the Lord God unto the ſons of men, that he hath not with-held his onely Son, but hath ſent him a Light into the world, that all men through him might believe, and be ſaved: But there is a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men in theſe our dayes that cannot endure ſound Doctrine, and ſuch will not receive him who is the good ſhepherd, but heaps unto themſelves Teachers having itching ears, which hath never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited them, nor never ſhall; and the abomination of deſolation, ſpoken of by <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet, ſtands now where it ought not; therefore I deſire thee who readeth theſe enſuing lines, to underſtand and weigh them in an equal Ballance, and with a ſingle eye look upon them, and thou wilt clearly ſee that here is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing written but what is juſt and true to every mans condition, without flattering, or daubing with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered Morter, as the falſe Prophets have done theſe many years, which hath made the abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo great in our Nation of ENGLAND. And
<pb facs="tcp:168503:3"/>
take heed of judging or cenſuring any thing haſtily, but try all things, (as he hath done who writ this unto thee) and hold faſt that which is good; For to this end was this ſent forth to publike view, That every one may be knowne by their fruits<hi>:</hi> From him who is a Friend to all that love the Truth as it is in JESUS called of men</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ambroſe Rigge.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168503:3"/>
            <head>THE BANNER OF GODS LOVE, AND ENSIGNE OF RIGHTEOVSNESS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as many dear and precious <note place="margin">Iſa. 8. 18. Joh. 17. 23.</note> Servants and Children of the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, whom he hath loved with an everlaſting love, and hath opened their eyes and ears to behold him whom they had pierced, and hath armed them with <note place="margin">Zach. 12. 10.</note> power from on High, to make war in righteouſneſs againſt all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <note place="margin">Rev. 20. 8, 9.</note> of darkneſs that ſtands up againſt the appearance of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168503:4"/>
Lamb of God, who hath now cloathed them with his Armor of Light and Life, and given them for an Helmet, the Hope <note place="margin">Rom. i3. 12. Eph. 6. 13, 17.</note> of Salvation, and hath put the Sword of the Spirit (which is the Word of God) into their mouths, that with boldneſs they may declare abroad the Name of him who is now come a Light into the World, and hath lighted every man that <note place="margin">Joh. 12. 46. Joh. 17. 9.</note> cometh into the World, that all men through him might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and come to the knowledge of the truth.</p>
            <p>And for this end is he now made manifeſt, To deſtroy the <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 8. Eccleſ. 12. 3: Ezek. 32. 25, 26: Ezek. 2i. 28.</note> Works that the devil hath wrought in man, even to make the ſtrong man bow before him, and the Keepers of the Houſe to tremble, that the uncircumciſed may fall by the ſtroke of his Sword which is now drawn in his hand, and made ready for a mighty ſlaughter, even to cut off the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Land of the living, that their remembrance may <note place="margin">Luk. i9: 27:</note> be blotted out from the earth, which wlil not that he ſhall rule whoſe right it is: and he hath made his children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants living Witneſſes of his eternal Truth, to declare his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Name among the Gentiles, and hath given them a <note place="margin">1 Joh. 5: 20: Luk. 22: 35:</note> good underſtanding to know him that is true, and hath ſent them forth into the VVorld vvithout Bag, or Scrip, or tvvo Coats, and hath given them his Word of Life and Light to declare to the Spirit in Priſon; and theſe have (as they have been moved of the Lord) run to and fro in the earth, in true and tender love to peoples ſouls, vvarning all men every <note place="margin">Acts 17: 30, 31. Acts 20: 33:</note> vvhere to repent, and ſeek the Lord vvhile he may be found, vvithout coveting any mans Silver, Gold, or Apparel; and for this have they been ſtocked, ſtoned, vvhipped, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſhamefully intreated, and not counted vvorthy to live upon the earth, not onely by them that profeſſed little or nothing of God, Chriſt, or the Scriptures, but rather by the Scribes, and Phariſees, and chief Prieſts, and zealous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors <note place="margin">Mark 8: 31:</note> as the Jevvs vvas, as may be vvitneſſed at this day by hundreds in our Nation of <hi>England,</hi> vvhoſe fruits ſhame their Profeſſion, and vvhoſe Works ſhevv to their faces they are of their Father the Devil. And thoſe vvhom the Lord <note place="margin">Joh. 8: 44: 1 Cor. 4: 2:</note> hath called and choſen to commit his ſecrets unto, and to place his eternal Name in, as they have freely received of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168503:4"/>
Lord, freely have they miniſtred unto all, whereby many hath been turned from darkneſſe unto light, and from the <note place="margin">Matth. i0. 8. Acts 26. 18.</note> power of Satan unto God; and God hath greatly bleſſed their labours within theſe few years, ſo that many that was ſcattered as Sheep without a Shepherd, in the cloudy and dark day, by the Idol dumb Sepherds which had made a prey <note place="margin">Ezek. 34: 12.</note> upon them, their feet are now directed into the Way of life and peace, wherein they are now walking up to <hi>Zion,</hi> with Songs of Deliverance, and are ſitting down with <hi>Abraham,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 35: 10:</note> 
               <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> in the Kingdom of God; and the children of the Kingdom ſhall be caſt out into utter darkneſs, where <note place="margin">Matth. 8: 11:</note> is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth for ever.</p>
            <p>And now quick and powerful hath the Word of the Lord <note place="margin">Heb. 4: 12:</note> been in the mouth of his Meſſengers and Miniſters in this Nation of <hi>England,</hi> and elſewhere, whereby the ſtrong man in hundreds hath been made to bow, and the Keepers of the Houſe to tremble; and by it hath the Wiſdom of the Wiſe <note place="margin">Iſa. 29: 14: 1 Cor. 1: 19: 1 Pet. 1: 23, 25: Iſa. 40: 8: Acts 19: 20:</note> been confounded, and the underſtanding of the prudent brought to nought; but the Word of the Lord hath ſtood, and ſhall ſtand and accompliſh the VVork for which it was ſent, and hath grown and encreaſed abundantly, ſo that many by it is quickned, and raiſed from death to life; and they have not laboured in vain, as the falſe Prophets have done this many years, but many Veſſels are full, and an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable multitude is drawn out of the Sea of confuſion, where <note place="margin">Luk. 5: 5, 6:</note> they were overwhelmed, and could never have come to the Son of God, unleſſe they had been drawn by the Cords of the Fathers Love, wherein now they walk to the praiſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God for evermore.</p>
            <p>And thoſe whom the Lord God of Heaven and Earth hath <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1<hi>:</hi> 22:</note> indued with his Spirit of Life and Light in Chriſt Jeſus his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son, and as they have been moved of the Lord, have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <note place="margin">Luk. 1: 1, 2:</note> in hand to ſet forth from the very firſt a Declaration in order of thoſe things which are moſt ſurely believed among us, who have been eye-witneſſes of him from the beginning, and of all the things that Jeſus began to do and to teach, of <note place="margin">Pſal. 112: 4:</note> the works and mighty wonders which he hath wrought for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168503:5"/>
the ſons of men, who ſate in darkneſſe and in the ſhadow of death, how he hath cauſed his everlaſting day to dawn upon them, and hath commanded light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, <note place="margin">Luke 1: 79: 2 Cor: 4: 6:</note> whereby his children comes to have the knowledge or his glory. And this Declaration hath been ſet forth for the ſake of the ſimple, that they may turn in at the call of Wiſdom, who is now uttering her Voice in the Streets, and opening <note place="margin">Prov. 1: 20, 22, 23, 24.</note> her Gate wide, ſo that many hearkens to her Voice, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in at her Gate; and by ſuch is <hi>Wiſdom</hi> juſtified daylie, <note place="margin">Matth. 11: 19: Iſa. 11: 9: Zech: 4: 9:</note> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> encreaſed abundantly, ſo that the Lord God is known to be one, and his Name one. And he hath confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his Work, not by Word onely but by his mighty <hi>Power,</hi> and by his Armor of Righteouſneſſe on the right hand, and on the left, whereby his Enemies is ſubdned under his feet, <note place="margin">2 Cor: 6, 7:</note> and the Power given unto him to rule whoſe right it is: And this hath his own Arm accompliſhed for his own Seed ſake which lay in captivity, and was oppreſſed and burthened, ſo <note place="margin">Ezek: 21: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7:</note> that it could not ariſe to bring forth fruit unto him, but his Vinyard wholly laid deſolate to the Beaſts of the field to make a prey upon, and his Heritage was become as a ſpeckled Bird that was wandered into the deſolate places of the earth, <note place="margin">Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: 2: 9:</note> and not one ſtone was found to build up the deſolation of <hi>Zion</hi> with, till it was hewed and ſuted by the Word of God, which is as a Hammer, which was put into the mouths of his choſen ones in the fulneſſe of time. <note place="margin">Jer: 23: 29:</note>
            </p>
            <p>And now I, with the reſt of my dear Brethren and Siſters, who have obtained grace and mercy from the Lord; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had perfect knowledge from the very firſt, of the things that Jeſus hath done for me, and the reſt, who have believed in his Name, and how it pleaſed the Father to reveal him in us, that we might preach him among the Gentiles, for the <note place="margin">Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: 16:</note> ſalvation of his people Iſrael, and for the redemption of all the children of <hi>Adam,</hi> who were made ſinners by his diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
            <p>Now am I moved of the Lord to bear my teſtimony (with the reſt of my Brethen and Siſters, who are in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers)</hi> unto Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the World, whom
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168503:5"/>
wee witneſſe in us, the hope of Glory and how He did there <note place="margin">Col. 1. 27.</note> begin his work, and wrought in us both the will and the deed, as our fore-Fathers witneſſed in their declaration in <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 13.</note> order; the miſtery that was hid from ages and generations was Chriſt in them the hope of glory, and them that ſought <note place="margin">Col. 1. 26.</note> a proofe of Chriſt in them, they exhorted to try themſelves, and prove themſelves, and told them that Chriſt was in them <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 3. 4. 5.</note> except they were reprobates; and this is the miſtery that is now hid from all ſorts of profeſſion and profeſſors at this day who are found without the life of Chriſt, manifeſted in the mortal fleſh, and ſo are ſeeking proofs of his ſpeaking <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 11. Deut. 18. 15. 18. Acts 3. 22.</note> in his people; and ſuch hath ears but doth not hear him of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote, which the Lord hath now raiſed to be a Teacher and a Leader to his people, which they now bear in all things according to the word of the Lord by the mouth of his ſervant <hi>Moſes:</hi> And this doth ſet all the world in an uproar ſo that <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> doth ſtrike hands together, <note place="margin">Rev. 20. 8. Rev. 17. 14. Rev. 12. 5. Rev. 19. 15. Matth. 3: 12: Luk. 3. 17</note> to joyn in Battle againſt the Lamb who is now ariſen to rule the nations with a Rod of Iron, and Fan, and purifie his Sons and Daughters, that he may gather his Wheat into his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner according to his promiſe, and burn up the Ghaff with unquenchable fire.</p>
            <p>And now ſhall they clearly be known that ſerveth the Lord in truth and tighteouſneſſe, from them who pretend <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 18. Titus 1. 16: 2 Tim: 43.</note> in words they know him, but in works deny him, for the time is already come wherein men cannot endure ſound Doctrine, but after their own luſts, heaps up unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <note place="margin">Iſa. 56: 10: 11: 12: Ier: 23: Ezetk 34: Matth: 23.</note> Teachers which doth not profit them at all, but are ſuch as the Prophets and Apoſtles of the Lord did always bear teſtimony againſt as all that are not wilfully blind may clearly ſee.</p>
            <p>But now hath the Lord furniſhed us with power from on high, to preach his everlaſting Goſple unto every creature, <note place="margin">Mark: 16: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</note> ſo that our labour and travel is to ſee Chriſt formed in them, who is the expreſſe image of his fathers perſon, that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth <note place="margin">Gal: 4: 19: Heb. 1: 3:</note> they might not be toſed to and fro, with every wind of Doctrine, through the ſleight of men but that all may <note place="margin">Eph: 4 14:</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:168503:6"/>
come to the knowledge of him in them, ſubduing all things under his feet, and leading Captivity Captive, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">1 Cor: 15:<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8: Ephe: 4: 8. Ephe: 5: 27.</note> and defacing the image of the Devil in all his children, that they may be preſented without ſpot unto his Father, and for this end did he ſow the good ſeed of the kingdom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, which the good ground hath received in us, and <note place="margin">Matth. 13. 8.</note> hath brought forth firſt the Blade, then the Ear, then the full corn in the Ear, to the everlaſting praiſe and glory of him that ſowed it; ſo that the earth hath brought forth her increaſe by handfulls, and abundance is gathered into the houſe of the Lord, and God hath opened the Windows of Heaven and hath ſent a bleſſing upon it, that there is ſcarce <note place="margin">Mall. 3. 10.</note> roome to hold it, and he hath rebuked the devourer in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds according to his promiſe, ſo that his children doth eat and drink with a diſcerning of his body, and are become one bread and one body fitly joyned together unto Chriſt the head, who is made unto them, wiſdome, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1 30:</note> ſanctification, and redemption, to the everlaſting praiſe of his everlaſting name for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>And now is the Lord ariſeing and ariſen out of his holy Habitation, and hath covered himſelfe with Zeale as with <note place="margin">Iſa: 59 7:</note> a Cloake, and for <hi>Zions</hi> ſake hath he uttered his voice as a man of Warr, whereby the tall Oakes hath been brought down, and the Cedars of Lebanon hath been made to bend; <note place="margin">Ezek. 37: 10: 11:</note> And he hath breathed upon the ſlain that they have ſtood up upon their feet, and are become the whole houſe of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa: 28: 17:</note> and for <hi>Zions</hi> ſake hath he laid Judgement to the line and righteouſneſſe to the plummet, and is ſweeping a way the refuge of lyes, ſo that there ſhall be no hideing place found in Heaven or in earth but his own righteouſneſſe, which whoſoever is found out of, in the day of Gods fierce wrath, ſhall be ſwept a way with the Beeſom of deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the Lake that burns with fire and brimſtone for ever, where there is no redemption. And therefore awake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvake all you carnal minded ones of what Sect or Faction ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you be of: The everlaſting day is come, and dawned upon us, which you hate, vvhich hath diſcovered you to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168503:6"/>
be out of Gods righteouſneſſe, in the deeds of darkneſs, following the Imaginations of your evil hearts, whereby the ſeed of God is oppreſsed, as a Cart is preſsed with <note place="margin">Amos 2: 13:</note> Sheaves, and over you death hath great dominion, and darkneſſe hath great power, the way of peace you know not, nor never can in that ſtate; therefore open your eyes, <note place="margin">Rev: 22. 16</note> and behold the bright and morning Star, that ariſeth out of the Eaſt, which is over-ſhadowing the whole earth, that every mans work is now made manifeſt of what ſort it is; and no longer ſhall your deeds be hid, for all things are naked and bare before him with whom we have to do; <note place="margin">Heb: 4: 13: 1 Cor. 4: 5:</note> and he will ſuddenly bring to light the hidden things of darkneſſe, ſo that every one ſhall appear as he is in truth and righteouſneſſe, or in deceit and unrighteouſneſſe, and all vailes will he rent, and all covers will he rip off, that his own flock only vvho are covered with his ſpirit of <note place="margin">Iſa: 30. 1:</note> life and power, may be hid in the day of his fierce wrath, which will come upon all mankind.</p>
            <p>Awake awake all you who hath long lain upon your beds of eaſe and carnal ſecurity, and hath eaten with the Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, <note place="margin">Amos 6: 3: 4: 5: Matt: 24. 49.</note> and drunken with the Drunkards, and is now beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Fiſt of wickedneſſe, and with a ſlanderous tongue backbiteing the innocent, behold your Maſter is come &amp; hath found you aſleep, He ſtands now at the door and knocks, and is deſiring of you to awake, and ariſe <note place="margin">Ephe: 5. 14.</note> out of the filthy pollutions of the world that you are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed in, that he may give you the light of life to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him into the Land of the living, where many now doth praiſe and magnifie his great Name for evermore, who hath done marvellous things for them who are his <note place="margin">Matt. 21. 42.</note> flock, who follows him whetherſoever he goes, unto whom He is a Prieſt, a Prophet, a King.</p>
            <p>Awake awake all you filthy Dreamers, who are in the defilements of the fleſh, and who hath made people bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh <note place="margin">Ier. 27 9. Iude 8:</note> by your falſe Dreams, which you have called the word of God, which hath been but a Divination of your own brain, and hath not profited the people at all, but their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168503:7"/>
hungry ſouls is yet languiſhing after the bread of life, you have fed your ſelves with the fatt, till your fleſh is become <note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 3. Ezek. 23. 20.</note> as the fleſh of Horſes, your eyes ſtand out with fatneſſe, your words is as ſmooth as butter, but in your heart doth the ravening Wolfe lye hid from the eyes of many, as your fruits doth daily manifeſt, the Lord will now feed <note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 16.</note> you with Judgement, and make you drink the dreggs of the Cup of his ſury, powred out without mixture, for you have cauſed many to erre by your lyes and lightneſs, and none have you brought into the knowledge of the truth, becauſe you have departed from it your ſelves, you have long ruled in this long night of Apoſtacy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the blind have walked which you have led, who have <note place="margin">Inter ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cos reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat ſtrabus.</note> called you miniſters of Chriſt and prophets of God: And of ſuch have you made a grievous prey, and hath taken their money for that which was not bread; but the Lord hath ſhaked his hand at your diſhoneſt gain, and hath cauſed <note place="margin">Ezek. 22. 13.</note> his everlaſting day to ſpring upon his children, which he hath appointed to gather from your mouths, that they <note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 22. 28.</note> ſhall no longer be made a prey upon by you; therefore be awakened and conſider your ſtate and condition in which you now ſtand, if you be not wholly given up to make Merchandize of peoples ſouls through covetouſneſſe which is Idolatry; for God will now no longer be mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <note place="margin">2 Peter. 2. 3.</note> ſuch as you ſow, ſuch ſhall you reap; your Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards are very unclean, Bryers, Thorns, Weeds, and <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 8.</note> Thiſtles grows up abundantly inſteed of tender Vines, you are ſleepy and ſloathful Vine-dreſſers, you may bluſh to look into your Vineyards if you were not wholly given up to hardneſſe of heart<hi>:</hi> The day of the Lord will come upon you as a thief in the night, wherein the Lord will <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 2.</note> require his ſheep at your hands, and then ſhall the book be opened wherein is written all your covetous practices, <note place="margin">Rev. 20. 12.</note> and ungodly deeds, and out of it ſhall you be judged ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and then ſhall you howle for pain of heart, and weep for griefe of ſpirit when you conſider how miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably you have deceived &amp; deluded many poore ſouls, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168503:7"/>
how you have ſcattered the Lords flock upon the barren Mountaines, which the Lord will ſurely require at your <note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 10.</note> hands; behold now the time is near accompliſhed that if you will not hear and lay it to heart, to give glory unto the Lord, that he will ſpread dung over your faces, and <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 2.</note> will curſe your bleſſings, yea many of them he hath curſed already, ſo that henceforth never fruit ſhall growe on you more, but you ſhall ſuddenly wither away like the Fig-tree that bare leaves, but no fruit, becauſe you have <note place="margin">Matt. 21. 19.</note> diſpiſed the Law of God, and hath followed after cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 14.</note> practices and are become curſed children who have forſaken the right way, and hath run gredily after the errors of <hi>Balaam</hi> the ſon of <hi>Boſor,</hi> whom Gods hand was heavily ſtretched out againſt, and the ſame hand of the Lord is againſt you now, who are found treading in the ſame ſteps.</p>
            <p>Awake awake all you high notioniſts of what kind or ſort ſoever who hath gotten the Scriptures of the Prophets and Apoſtles to talk of in your ayrie minds, and thinks to have eternal life in them, but hates the ſon of God in all <note place="margin">Iohn 5. 39.</note> his appearances, and will not come unto him that you might have life; the day is dawned, and the ſun is riſen with his burning heat and hath ſcorched all your beauty, ſo <note place="margin">Ier. 17 6.</note> that you are become as a parched Heath in the Drought of Summer, all your glory is the Lord bringing into <note place="margin">Iſa. 23. 9.</note> contempt, and your Wiſdome hath he turned into fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſſe, becauſe neither you nor it did ſtand in the fear of his name; your preaching and long praying are but as the cutting off of a Doggs neck, or offering Svvines blood; <note place="margin">Iſa. 66. 3.</note> the Lord hath no regard to it becauſe your hands is pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and daily vvorks iniquity: And as a Cage is full of birds, ſo is your houſes and hearts full of deceit, your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Idols have you not yet caſt to the moles, and <note place="margin">Iſa. 2. 20.</note> to the Batts, for the fear of the Lord &amp; for the glory of his majeſty, vvho is novv ariſen to ſhake terribly the earth, the Lord vvill not be mocked vvith your Hypocritical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <note place="margin">Gall. 6. 7.</note> for the day is come vvherein every one of your
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168503:8"/>
works are made manifeſt, but this you cannot endure to hear of, who loves darkneſſe rather then light becauſe <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 19.</note> your deeds are evil, therefore be awakened, be awakened now when the everlaſting day is come and conſider your ſtate, and meaſure your wayes, by the unalterable rule of righteousneſſe, which is the light wherewith you are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 13. 15.</note> and it will let you ſee that you never yet knew the miſtery of the Croſſe of Chriſt, which to the world doth crucifie all that comes to bear it; but in the world and the vanityes therof are you yet wandering as ſheep <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 14.</note> without a ſhepheard, and never yet witneſſed a true ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration to God with the light of his Son: And now are you ſtumbling at the ſtumbling ſtone that is laid in <hi>Zion,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 8. 14. 1 Pet. 2. 8.</note> which is become a rock of offence to you who ſtumble at the word of faith which is nigh in the heart; your high buildings ſhall be now laid beſolate and not one ſtone left upon another, that ſhall not be thrown down, the mouth of the Lord of Hoſts hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <p>Awake awake all you covetous cruel oppreſſors, who grinde the faces of the poore, and by Cuzening, Chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 14. 15.</note> and defrauding, hath ſet your neſts on high, and are become great in the earth, ſo that you joyn houſe to houſe and field to field, till there be no place for the poore in the earth, the day is come upon you that you <note place="margin">Iſa. 5. 7. 8.</note> ſhall be called to an account before the dreadful God of Heaven and earth, who hath taken notice of all your wayes and actings, and hath heard the cry of the poore and needy which you have greedily made a prey upon, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as you could receive power from the beaſt whoſe Image you bear: And therefore go to now ye rich men, weepe and howle for the miſery that is coming upon you, for the ruſt of your ſilver and gold ſhall be a witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Iames 5. 1. 2. 3.</note> you; the Lord is now bringing down the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and ſetting the oppreſſed free, which hath long cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him; your riches ſhall not deliver you in the day of Gods fierce vvrath: Therefore novv, incline your ears <note place="margin">Pro. i1: 4: Ezek: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: 6. and 18 30.</note> unto the call of Wiſdome, and repent repent vvith ſpeed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168503:8"/>
and return unto the Lord with all your hearts, and ſeek him while he may be found, and hearken unto him while he calls upon you, <hi>Why will ye dye in your iniquities?</hi> Now have you all a day and a time, ſee that you all prize it, leaſt <note place="margin">Pſal. 52, 5.</note> you be cut off from the Land of the living, and go down to the pit with the uncircumciſed.</p>
            <p>And now bleſſed be the everlaſting Day for ever, who hath viſited us who ſate in darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of <note place="margin">Luk. 1. 78, 79.</note> death, &amp; hath broken forth in an acceptable time unto the ſons of men after this long night of Apoſtacy, wherein darkneſs hath been called light, and the Way of the Lord hath not been known, nor the true Prophet which <hi>Moſes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 3. 22, 23.</note> wrote of, hath not been heard; but people hath been ever learning, but were never able to come to the knowledge of the truth, which many hath deſired to know and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, <note place="margin">2 Tim 3:</note> but could not in that ſtate, and by reaſon of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and blindneſs of mind, have followed ſuch Teachers as have been wholly Enemies to Jeſus Chriſt, and in every thing out of his Doctrine, but yet covered themſelves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with the ſheeps clothing, and through good words, and fair ſpeeches, deceived the hearts of the ſimple, and <note place="margin">Rom i6. 18.</note> made them believe that they were the only men that were gifted of God to miniſter a Word in ſeaſon to the weary, and to direct them that were gone aſtray, into the Way of <note place="margin">Ezek. 38. 16.</note> God: And ſo great was the Cloud of darkneſs over the whole earth, and the covering was drawn ſo cloſe over the ravening Wolf in them, that he did not at all appear unto the children of men, but they gave large ſums of money unto them, and thought by that to know the true way to eternal life; and this kept the ravening Wolf from appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or breaking forth, ſo that (as they did imagine) all was well, and at peace, and they cryed peace, peace, unto <note place="margin">Ezek. 13. 10.</note> them that put into their mouths, and daubed with untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Morter; ſo the Lord overturned them by his mighty power, and then did he appear in a meaſure of the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of his love unto a people that was called <hi>Puritans,</hi> and he opened their eyes in a little meaſure, that they ſaw
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168503:9"/>
the deceit and unrighteouſneſs that both prieſt and people lived in; they had a zeal for God and his glory, and a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of affection aroſe in their hearts one to another, to exhort one another to love, and to good Works, and the Seed of the Kingdom of God was ſown in them; but it falling by the way-ſide, the Fowles of the air picked it a-away, ſo that it came not to take root downward, nor <note place="margin">Mar. 4 4.</note> bring forth fruit upward to him that ſowed it. So theſe fell back again, and loſt their zeal and tenderneſs which they had, and got the words of truth in the airy mind, but in the life was one with the World after a little time; and then was the Lord grieved that his Heritage was wholly <note place="margin">Jer. 12. 8.</note> left deſolate for the Fowls of the Air to tread under their feet, and make a prey upon; and it pittyed him to ſee his own ſeed ſo oppreſſed, and his Vinyard ſo wholly laid waſte to the Beaſts of the field. <note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And then did he ariſe for his own Name ſake, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the eyes of many, and appeared in a large meaſure into a People that was called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and ſhewed them in a large meaſure the Witchcraft of the great Whore, who <note place="margin">Rev. 17. 1, 2.</note> had made all Nations drunk with the Wine of her Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and then did he lead them from the mouths of the Idol dumb ſhepherds which had made a prey upon them, and had taken their money for that which they ſaw was not bread, nor had not in the leaſt ſatisfied their hungry <note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 2.</note> ſouls; even then did God raiſe his living Witneſs in them, and ſhed his eternal love abroad in their hearts, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them together in ſeveral quarters of the world, and his Name was witneſſed among them, and his Power did appear in them, and a great zeal and tenderneſs for a while was among them, ſo that they met with part of the rage of the Devil, and indured it for a time with joy; and while they was near unto the Lord, he was known to be near un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and gave them the necks of their Enemies to tread upon, and a great ſight of the good Land they had, and the Seed of the Kingdom of God was abundantly ſown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, but it falling upon the ſtony ground in them <note place="margin">Mar. 4. 5.</note>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168503:9"/>
when the Sun aroſe vvith his burning heat, it vvas ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and became unfruitful, ſo that after a time the povver of God ceaſed, and vvas not ſeen amongſt them, but coldneſs and barrenneſs got up, and pride, and exaltation, and ſelf-conceitedneſs crept in by little and little, and then they begun to build again thoſe things vvhich they had in a meaſure deſtroyed; and he that got the moſt in his brain-knovvledge, vvas ſet up to be a Teacher and a Ruler, and ſo gloryed in the gift more then in the Giver; and this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry became one in nature vvith the Prieſts, and did not profit the people at all, vvhich may be vvitneſſed at this day. And novv are they ſet dovvn at eaſe in a dead form of that vvhich the Saints vvitneſſed the life of; nay, they have ſo far departed from the povver of God vvhich the Saints did, &amp; doth vvitneſs to lead &amp; guide them, that they have loſt the very form, and are become one in nature vvith the World, and differ nothing but in vvords, and in outward ſhews and pretences. The true Proverb is fulfilled. upon them, <hi>The Dog is turned to his own Vomit again; and the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 22. Prov. 26. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Sow that was waſhed to her wallowing in he Myre; ſo that the Lord is weary with their ſacrifices, and their ſolemn Aſſemblies he cannot away with, becauſe they have cast his righteous Law</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 11. to 16. Heb. 10. to 29.</note> 
               <hi>behind their backs, and hath trodden under foot the blood of the Covenant, and now hath ſitten down in a reſt which is pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, and are become enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the ſame hand of the Lord that vvas turned againſt his Enemies before, the ſame is lifted up againſt them novv, vvhereby they are torn and rent as an old Garment, and as a tottering VVall that is daubed vvith untempered Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And thus have they rendred unto the Lord evil for all his kindneſs, and hath turned his grace into laſciviouſneſs, vvhich vvould have led them to ſalvation if they had been taught vvith it, vvhereby the vvorks of the Devil <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11. 12.</note> vvould have been deſtroyed in them, vvhich they are ſo ſtrongly pleading for, and concluding all to be deceived and ſeduced that ſhall vvithſtand or oppoſe it; and if any vvill not bovv dovvn to their Image vvhich they have ſet
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168503:10"/>
up from the Scripture Letter, preſently he is judged and cenſured not vvorthy to have communion vvith, though he have the povver of God for his defence, and be led and guided by the Spirit of the living God, and have fellovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip vvith him, and be brought into his Covenant of light and life.</p>
            <p>And this is that now which they call their Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, Baptiſm of Water, and taking of material Bread and Wine, which there is no command for throughout the Scripture; but Judgement, Mercy, and Faith is omitted, <note place="margin">Luk. 11. 49.</note> which is the weighty matters of the Law, and ſo the Wo that was unto their forefathers is to the ſame generation ſtill. And thus hath the Lord been mocked with a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary humility, and a Will-Worſhip after the traditions of men, after the Rudiments of the World, and not after Chriſt the Light of the World, who hath lighted every man that cometh into the World: And ſo now are they <note place="margin">Joh. 1. 9.</note> crying up the Ordinances of God, the Ordinances of God, as the Jews did the Temple, but are as ignorant of Chriſt Jeſus the Subſtance, as the Jews was that ſtoned him: Though there was a time that he was known in ſuch things, and in the fleſh, yet he that came through it, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to know him ſo no more; but theſe deny all that comes to know him ony otherwiſe, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did them that te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified againſt the outward Temple, (which was a time commanded of God) when their Bodies was made the Temples of God, and they came to witneſs the Subſtance <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 19.</note> of the Figure. Now this is the reaſon of ſo much confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion now among ſeveral ſorts of men and forms, That the Life and Subſtance of all Types, Shadows, and Figures, is denyed, and only the Husk fed upon; and this hath been the ruine and down-fall of theſe people that are called <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then in another diſpenſation of the Lords love did he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to a People called <hi>Independents,</hi> &amp; brought many of them to ſe the emptineſs of all ſorms of profeſſion, &amp; they thought only to depend upon the Lord was the ſafeſt way;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168503:10"/>
and there was a love begot in them to God and his Way and truth, and tenderneſs of ſpirit one towards another, and they were a little brought low in their own eyes, and they ſeparated themſelves in the outward from other men in Worſhip; but it was ſelf that ſeparated them, which was never yet denyed nor ſeparated from by them, as doth ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear at this day in their whole courſe of life; the Seed of the Kingdom was ſown among them, but they receiving <note place="margin">Mark 4. 7.</note> it into the thornie ground it was choaked ere it grew up, with the cares of the World, and deceitfulneſs of riches, and abominable pride, envy, and wrath, as <hi>Nathaniel Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon,</hi> one of their great Sect-Maſters of the Town and County of <hi>Southampton,</hi> may bear me witneſs, if his heart be not totally hardneed, and he be given up to work all manner of wickedneſs with greedineſs, and his conſcience be ſeared with a hot Iron.</p>
            <p>Wofully hath theſe ſort of people betrayed their truſt, their latter end will be worſe by double then was their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; highly are they now exalted upon the Mountains of pride, and deeply are they obliged in the bond of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity; their Sacrifices are now an abomination to the Lord, who is of purer eyes then to behold iniquity; they have departed from the counſel of the Lord, &amp; have great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly erred into the Way of <hi>Cain,</hi> as will hereafter plainly <note place="margin">Jude 11.</note> appear in <hi>Nathaniel Robbinſon,</hi> and many of his Hearers <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 4. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> in the Town of <hi>Hampton,</hi> who are now become brutiſh, and without natural affection, incontinent, fierce deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, and not onely ſo, but hath a great thirſt after their blood, without any juſt cauſe, as hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appeared both in words and actions not long ſince; all this they cover under a cover of profeſſion, and a feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed humility, which is ſeen with the children of light to be double hypocriſie. And a covering of a moſt curious co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour <note place="margin">Matth. 7. 15, 16.</note> have they put on to hide this ravening Wolf, but now it is too narrow, the ravenous Beaſt breaks forth in great rage and fury, and muſters up all his Forces againſt the Lambs appearance, who is now come to torment him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168503:11"/>
his time. And now doth he caſt out floods of railings, revilings, lyes, ſlanders, falſe accuſations after the Woman in whom the man-child is moving, and this is becauſe his ſacrifice is not accepted: But oh <hi>Cain!</hi> why art thou wrath? and why is thy countenance fallen? Why doth thou ſo rage and ſwell, foame and torment thy ſelf, and envy thy Brother? If thou doſt well thou ſhall be accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; if not, ſin lyeth at thy door. Thou haſt forgotten that <note place="margin">Gen 4. 5, 6.</note> thou ſhould firſt be reconciled to thy Brother before thou offer thy gift, and this is the main reaſon why it is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted at thy hand, which makes thee ſo envious and wrathful, that even nothing will quench thy thirſty ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack but thy Brothers blood, which daylie appears to all that are not wilfully blind, by thy eager purſuance after it, and threatning them that will not to the utmoſt anſwer thy curſed deſires in perſecuting the innocent. Oh how art thou poſtng on in the Way of <hi>Cain</hi> the Murtherer, <note place="margin">Jude 11.</note> and treading in the ſteps of thy Father <hi>Balaam!</hi> Oh thou <hi>Nathaniel Robbinſon!</hi> Oh how is the right Wayes of the Lord evil ſpoken of and reviled daylie by thee, and by thy ſeduced followers, who makes lyes your refuge and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief your dwelling place, which is hatched in your deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Breaſts! Wil your high talking of God and Chriſt cover all this? Or are you ſo given up to believe a lye as to believe it will? There is an eye opened that ſees you, which you ſee not; and a Judge that weighs your actions, which you know not; but when the Book of every one of your conſciences ſhall be opened, then out of that ſhall you all be judged, without reſpect of perſons, and receive according to your deeds done in the body. In that day ſhall not your crying Lord, Lord, and preaching in the Name of Chriſt in your Synagogues reſcue you from that dreadful ſentence, <hi>Depart from me ye workers of iniquity, I know you not; for I was an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 7. 23. Matth. 25. 41, 42, 43, 44. By Name <hi>VVilliam Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and ye fed me not; I was thirſty, and ye gave me no drink; a ſtranger, and ye took me not in,</hi> but went with abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lyes and falſe reports to the Magiſtrates to perſecute me as a Wanderer and a Deluder; and when they would
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168503:11"/>
not impriſon me, you cauſed them to do it; and when there was no Witneſs againſt me, you came in falſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eliz. Horſent</hi> ſaid it was a matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience not to viſit her Siſter in Priſon.</note> Witneſſes your ſelves, whereby to ſeek my ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and when I was in priſon, ſome of you ſaid it was a matter of conſcience not to viſite me, and ſaid it was juſt upon me: All this and more have you acted and ſpoken againſt me, becauſe you neither knew the Father, nor me; for in as much as you have done this to one of the leaſt <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 45, 46. Matth. 18. 6.</note> that believe in me, you have done it to me: <hi>And therefore now wo unto you, good had it been for you that a Milſtone had been hanged about your necks, and you caſt into the midſt of the Sea, then to have offended one of them that believe in me. Oh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 23. 37, 38.</note> 
               <hi>how often would I have gathered you as a Hen gathereth her Chickens under her Wings, and ye would not,</hi> but hated, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted and ſhamefully intreated my ſervants and meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that I ſent in tend or love unto you, to warn you, while you had a day and time, to turn unto me from all your abominations: <hi>But oh! how have you hated reproof,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1. 21. Iſa. 55. 9.</note> 
               <hi>and turned your ear from the cry of Wiſdom, and hath choſen your own wayes, which is corrupt, before me, and as far from mine as the Heaven is from the earth!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh how will you anſwer this, ye ſtiff-necked and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious people, that have eyes, and ſee not; ears, and hear not; and hearts, and doth not underſtand! Will the Lord be mocked with your vain oblations which you bring be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 13.</note> him day by day, when your hands is full of blood, and your hearts is after your Idols? <hi>You have ſet your Neſts on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 30. 1.</note> 
               <hi>high, and hath covered your ſelves with a covering, but not with the Spirit of the Lord,</hi> as is daylie apparent to all whoſe eyes the Lord hath opened; highly are you ſeated upon the Mountains of pride and exaltation; the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> did far exceed you in zeal, who made clean the outſide, which you are far from; but you ſay pride is in the heart, which is true enough by your garments; you are bad pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns before them you call Heathens, which can ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the outſide; yea, many of them outſtrips you in life and converſation, and would be aſhamed of your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168503:12"/>
You have built you a Tower, whoſe top you think may reach to Heaven, whereby to get you a Name, and exalt your ſelves in the ſight of men; and a name you have gotten of Lambs and Sheep, but the nature of Dogs and Swine is found ruling in you, as is too too evidently your <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 1.</note> actions and fruits: I know you wil call this railing, but it is the Words of ſound Doctrine unto you, which you can ſcarce endure, you have been ſo long daubed with untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Morter, and flattered in your iniquity; but now will <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 3.</note> the Lord rip off all your falſe covers, and your folly ſhall be made manifeſt unto all men, as theirs was who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 8, 9,</note> the truth in former ages.</p>
            <p>I did think to cover your iniquity from the eyes of the World, but now I ſee the Lord will not have it ſo, but your ſhame and confuſion muſt now be laid open unto all, that others may hear, and fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and take warning, and that you may be left without excuſe, and your blood be upon your own heads in the day of the Lords fierce indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which ſhall come upon you as a thief in the night, except you with ſpeed repent, and turn to the Lord with all your hearts, and with all your ſouls, and put on Sackcloth, and ſit down in the duſt; for the jealouſie of the Lord is kindled againſt you, and all your prayers are an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination to him; for you regard iniquity, and envy in your hearts, and works it with your hands: Is now the Weapon of your Warfare become a Magiſtrates Sword? Wil not your Miniſtry ſtand without impriſoning and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the innocent? Had ever the Churches of Chriſt ſuch a VVeapon, as you can read of? VVhat will be the end of theſe things? Conſider betime, if you be not wholly given up to a reprobate mind. In true and tender love to your poor ſouls I ſpeak, &amp; warn you again, as I have often done, who have moſt unjuſtly ſuffer'd by you, both in falſe words, and unjuſt actions, as I ſhal make appear to publike view<hi>:</hi> You have caſt many falſe and abominable aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons upon us who are by you in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and moſt eſpecially upon me, who am onely known to you by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168503:12"/>
the Name of <hi>Ambroſe Rigge;</hi> yea many things have you laid to my charge, which I never knew nor acted, for which the Lord wil you judge, which thing you never made good, to this day, nor never can. And this have you poſſeſt ignorant people with, <hi>That we are Witches and Deluders, and doth deny Chriſt and the Scriptures;</hi> and many other filthy things, which is not fit to be named, but to be thrown into the bottomleſs pit from whence they came: And this have you poſſeſſed the minds of many with, for which the Lord will reward you into your own boſoms; but of all your falſe Accuſations are we clear in the preſence of the Lord, for Chriſt and the Scriptures we own and witneſs, elſe we ſhould not ſee your deceit and hypocriſie, which is cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in you with the Name of Religion; and if we did not own him in us the hope of glory, we needed not ſuffer by <note place="margin">Col. 1. 26, 27.</note> you and all the World ſo much reviling and ſlandering, and be hated with a deadly hatred, as we are daylie by you; but at this we marvel not, for we know it was our Maſters portion before of the ſame generation, as we have a cloud of Witneſſes recorded in the Scripture of truth, was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our admonition and learning, as our forefathers were moved of the Holy Ghoſt, took in hand to ſet forth in order a declaration of the ſufferer, &amp; of the perſecutor, that we might have a Witneſſe for one, and againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which we prize greatly at this day, ſeeing that both parts is now to be fulfilled, as your eyes have ſeen, and our ears have heard.</p>
            <p>And thus hath the third ground appeared worſe then both the former, wherein you are found who are called <hi>Independents;</hi> for you are weighed in the Ballance of the <note place="margin">1 Sam 2. 3.</note> Sanctuary, and are found wanting; therefore wo unto you if ye do not repent, for the Spirit of the Lord will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 3.</note> ſtrive with you, nor his Meſſengers will not alwaies be ſent to warn you to turn unto him; but the time ſhall ſuddenly come upon you, that you ſhall ſeek the Word of the Lord from Sea, to Sea and ſhall not find it, if you ſtill <note place="margin">Amos 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11, 12.</note> go on in hard heartedneſs and rebellion, and deſpiſe the day of your viſitation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:168503:13"/>
And now <hi>Nathaniel Robbinſon,</hi> I ſhall lay open ſome of thy fruits to publike view, that all who feare God, and keep his commandments, may be aſhamed of thee. And this I ſhall declare for the ſimple ſake, that they may know thee by thy fruits, according to the words of Chriſt, <hi>Matt.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 7. 15, 16.</note> 7. 20. and that all who loves their ſouls may no longer be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by thee, nor hold thee up, leſt they partake with thee of thy plagues.</p>
            <p>Upon the firſt day of the Week I who am called of the World by the Name of <hi>Ambroſe Rigge,</hi> was moved of the Lord to come into the Idols-Temple where thou was ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a divination of thy own brain, where I ſtood peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly till thou had made an end, as many may witneſſe; and then I ſpoke to thee the words of truth in ſoberneſs, but thou fled out at a back-door, as the falſe hirelings ever did; <note place="margin">Joh. 10. 13.</note> and then thoſe that was preſent in hearing thee, fell upon me like ſo many Wolves and Lyons, that it was the great love and mercy of the Lord that I ſaved my blood; and they haled me out of thy Synagogue into the Street, where I was ſpeaking the Words of truth with boldneſſe, till one of thy Hearers, by name <hi>William Pinhorne,</hi> and <hi>Nathaniel Knight,</hi> one of thy members came, and laid violent hands on me, and haled me violently along the Streets to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jors Houſe, where they kept me priſoner till the Major came home, and then accuſed me falſly to the Major, ſo they ſent me to priſon, where I did remain till the ſecond daie, and then was brought before the ſaid Major and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Town and Countie of <hi>Southampton,</hi> where did appear none to lay any thing to my charge worthie of bonds: Then came in <hi>Nathaniel Robbinſon,</hi> as a Judge in his own cauſe, and told the Magiſtrates he would prove me a Hireling; and when I put him to prove it, he quoted that place of Scripture in <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. where Chriſt ſaid unto his Diſciples when he ſent them forth without bag, or ſcrip, or two Coats, and commanded them to eat and drink ſuch things as was ſet before them, for the Labourer is worthie of his hire; but when I put him to prove by the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168503:13"/>
Scripture where ever Chriſt commanded his Miniſters to go into ſuch a City, and there have a ſet-place, and a Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-houſe to go into, and have fifty pounds by the Year from the State, which is his practice, as many may witneſs, ſuch a command was not to be found thorowout the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Now let any that are guided by the Spirit of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, judge whether of theſe are according to the command of Chriſt, or agreeable to the Scriptures of truth and the practiſe of the holy men of God.</p>
            <p>Then when the Magiſtrates could find no juſt occaſion of evil againſt me, whereby to ſuffer anyfurther impriſonment, <hi>Nathaniel Robbinſon</hi> came &amp; told them in my hearing, they had beſt to bind me to my Good-behavior, when no evil-behavior could juſtlie be laid to my charge: And then they would have proceeded againſt me for miſ-behavior; but I pleaded my freedom according to their own Law, That without the mouth of two or three Witneſſes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is eſtabliſhed or proved, nor cannot legallie be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted. So upon that they concluded to ſend me to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon again, which was done accordinglie. Then on the next daie came <hi>Nathaniel Robbinſon</hi> and another Prieſt to the Priſon-door, and asked me if they might have a little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with me, to which I anſwered. Yea<hi>:</hi> So they went awaie, and ſaid they would come again by and by, which they never did, and ſo proved themſelves to be of their Father the Devil, who was a liar from the beginning, and abode not in the truth: Then I was ſent for before the Magiſtrates again, where was five falſe Witneſſes prepared againſt me, of which <hi>Nathaniel Knight</hi> was one; but their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie did not agree together, as it was with their forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers recorded in the Scripture of truth, <hi>Mar.</hi> 14. 56, to 59. Then the Magiſtrates being more ſober then to proſecute from ſuch falſe Witneſſes, they commanded their abſence; then they tendered me the Oath of Abjuration, which I did then, and ſhall for ever bear teſtimonie againſt, both over my ſelf in particular, and over the whole Church of God in general: So finding no juſt occaſion againſt me
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168503:14"/>
of farther Bonds, they ſet me free, according to Law, though it was much againſt the Wills of mine adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>Then on the third daie of the ſeventh Month, 1657. <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin Embree</hi> went to the Steeple-houſe in <hi>Southampton,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Roods,</hi> and there ſtayed peaceablie until the Prieſt had ended both his Sermon and Prayer, as he called it; and when he had quite ended, as ſhe did believe, ſhe ſpake ſome few words to the people whereupon two of the Juſtices of the ſaid Town, preſently commanded ſome Officers to lay hands upon her, which they did, and haled her in a rude manner through the Streets to priſon, without any Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination or Mittimus to the Officer or Keeper of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to ſhew the cauſe of her impriſonment, nor had the Keeper any Warrant for her detainment in priſon, where ſhe remained until the Seſſions, which began the <hi>17th.</hi> of that Month; and in the Evening of that day the Recorder <hi>Liſle</hi> ſent one of the Town-Officers to bring her before the Court; and calling for the Indictment laid againſt her, it was anſwered, There was none; whereupon the Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der taxed the Juſtices for having impriſoned her wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and ſo word was ſent preſently back, not to bring her to the Court; but the next day there was a falſe Indictment framed contrary to the late Act, by which ſhe ſuffered for the words maliciouſly, wilfully, or of purpoſe, (according to the Act) was quite left out of the Indictment, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Word <hi>diſturbance</hi> put in, upon which Indictment the Jury proceeded, and brought her in guilty of diſturbance; whereupon the Recorder <hi>Liſle</hi> gave ſentence to lay a Fine of five pounds upon her to be paid at a Months time, or to be ſent to the Houſe of Correction for ſix months, to be ſet to hard labour, &amp; be corrected according as they ſhould think fit; but the Priſoner replying ſhe would never pay any, they had her body there preſent, they might do with her what they thought good; ſo ſhe asking whether ſhe was free, they bid her go home if ſhe would, which ſhe did.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:168503:14"/>
Now the Month being up, the Mayor of the Town made out his Warrant to the Conſtables and Beedles to come to her houſe to demand the mony, or to take her Body; her Name being miſtaken in the VVarrant, there was nothing done, only the payment of the Fine refuſed: Then two days after; being the 21. of the eighth month, the Conſtable &amp; five or ſix Officers with Swords, came with a ſecond VVarrant from the Mayor to fetch her to <hi>Bridewell;</hi> but ſhe being in an inner Room in her houſe, did forbear putting her ſelf in their hands, and ſo remains, expecting what fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe they will take againſt her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anne Horſent</hi> upon the <hi>6th.</hi> day of the <hi>7th.</hi> Month, was moved of the Lord to go to a Steeplehouſe in <hi>Hampton,</hi> called <hi>All-Saints,</hi> where <hi>Nathaniel Robbinſen</hi> ſpoke that day, where ſhe ſtood peaceably, and ſpoke not a word un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til <hi>Robbinſon</hi> was come down his Pulpit, and out of the Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-place, and when he was fled, ſhe ſpoke ſome few words to the people, and ſo went home again. But the next day this <hi>Robbinſon</hi> ſent to the Church-VVardens, (as they are called) telling them he had been affronted, and if they did not execute their Office, he would complain againſt them<hi>:</hi> [Take notice of that, thou that reads, with a ſingle eye] And he alſo went to the Mayor of the Town with a falſe Information againſt her the ſaid <hi>Anne,</hi> whereupon the Mayor ſent his Officers to apprehend her where ſhe was to viſit the ſaid <hi>Ellin Embree</hi> in priſon, and there they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo detained her in priſon until the Seſſiont, full 12. dayes, and was likewiſe impriſoned without Examination, or any Accuſers heard, and was proceeded againſt in the ſame manner, and upon the ſaid dayes and VVarrant as the ſaid <hi>Ellin Embree,</hi> although it did not appear by any proofs in the Court, that ſhe the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> had diſturbed the ſaid <hi>Robbinſon</hi> in the time of his officiating, nor yet in going to it, or returning from it, as many can witneſſe; nor can <hi>Robbinſon</hi> ſay that he heard any one vvord that ſhe ſaid in the Meeting-place, but was got home, or very near, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168503:15"/>
ſhe ſpake; yet judgement was given againſt her at the Seſſions, either to pay five pounds, or to be ſent to the Houſe of Correction, to be ſet at hard labour, and be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected as they ſhould think fit, though it could not truly be brought in that ſhe had broke any Law.</p>
            <p>Note, That the Juſtices of the Town (when they were in priſon) did give order to the Keeper of the Priſon, that none ſhould viſite them but their near Relations.</p>
            <p>Therefore I deſire all ſober people in this Nation that fears the Lord, to weigh and conſider theſe things, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever ſuch a Miniſtry as this was ever ordained of God yea or nay, that will not ſtand without impriſoning and perſecuting the innocent for ſaying not a word, but for ſtanding peaceably among the reſt, looking upon him; What do you think is in this mans heart if he could but get the Rulers and Scribes to join with him in cruelty? Would not the Jeſuit Prieſts in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> dayes been aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to have acted ſuch things againſt any that came to ſpeak to them? Oh <hi>Nathaniel Robbinſon!</hi> cannot thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven bluſh to hear of this? Is thy heart ſo hardened that thou glories in that which one day will be thy ſhame? What will be the end of theſe things? Conſider betime, left he that thou ſo much ſtrives againſt, break thee to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and thou be caſt out into utter darkneſs, where is weeping, wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:168503:15"/>
               <hi>THere dyed of late one</hi> John Behaute, <hi>in the Town and County of Southampton, who was another of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Teachers, as this</hi> Nathaniel Robbinſon <hi>aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, who did upon his death-bed declare, that this</hi> Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon <hi>was the cauſe of his death, to</hi> Robbinſons <hi>face, but did forgive him, and bid him do ſo no more: Now if they be ſo envious one to another, as be the cauſe of one anothers death, what may any judge they would do with us if they had power given them from above? If this be not</hi> Cain's <hi>way that</hi> Robbinſon <hi>is in, let all who feares the Lord, judge, Gen.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>Jude</hi> 11.</p>
            <div type="warning">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:168503:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>And now a few words in warning to the Prieſts Profeſſors, and people of the Town, and County of</hi> South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampton.</head>
               <p>VVOE Woe unto you the Inhabitants of <hi>Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Prieſts Profeſſors and People, who hate the light wherewith Chriſt Jeſus the light of the world hath <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 19, 20, 21. Pſalm. 73, 18. Iohn 2. 8, 9. 1 Iohn 1. 5.</note> lighted you withall; your deeds are evil, and your wayes are crooked, and perverſe, even the ſlippery wayes of darkneſſe, your building muſt be thrown down, and not one ſtone left upon another, &amp; your Image muſt be daſhed to peices which you have ſet up, (unto which you would <note place="margin">Dan. 3. 23. 1 Pet. 2. 6, 7, 8.</note> have the true ſeed to bow) with the little ſtone cut out of the Mountains without hand; at which you ſtumble, which is become a rock of offence unto you, who at the word of life ſtumbles, and yet profeſſeth the letter as your fore-fathers did, but as far if not further from owning <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 33.</note> the life as they were, even ſtoping your ears, at the voice of the true Prophet; and cannot endure ſound Doctrine; <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 3. 4. Iſa. 48. 22.</note> but ſaith unto the Prophets Propheſy ſmooth things unto us, and ſpeake unto us peace, though the witneſſe of God (the true Prophet in your conſciences) ſaith there is no peace to you, for you live in the luſt of the eye, and in <note place="margin">Ezek. 10. 49.</note> the luſt of the fleſh, and in the pride of life, eating and drinking and riſeing up to play, even like your Siſter <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> whom God overthrew: And doth not thy Prophets in the midſt of thee hearken to this, and cry peace peace where the Lord hath not ſpoken peace, and daube with untempred morter, ſo that none is able to turn from the <note place="margin">Ier. 6. 13, 14, 15.</note> evil of their doings, but all your daubing is accounted as Potters clay, for within are you ful of rottenneſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, <note place="margin">Ezek. 13, 10, i1, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> pride, and ambition, envy and hatred, priſoning
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168503:16"/>
and perſecuting the Innocent, which are all fruits of that <note place="margin">Matt. 23, 27, 28. Matt, 7. 19, 20. Heb. 6. 8.</note> tree which hath no promiſe but to be hewn down and caſt into the fire; long hath the Lord looked for fruits of you, but nothing is brought forth but Bryers, and Thornes, for your profeſſion and Miniſtry will not ſtand, without renting and tearing, pulling and hailing out of your Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, perſecuting and drawing the Innocent before your Iudgement ſeates; falſe accuſeing and backbiteing, <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9</note> lyeing and ſlandering, theſe are the fruits that is brought forth a mongſt you of which I am an eye and eare witneſſe, and this was not declared againſt by thee <hi>Nathaniell Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> who profeſſes thy ſelfe to be a teacher of others, but thou thy ſelfe is not yet taught to deny nor to declare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch things, but doth cry out and complain it is not ſevere enough; Now are you like Prieſt like people, all are <note place="margin">Ier. 23. i1. Hoſea 4. 9.</note> prophaine; yea your wickedneſſe is now found out, and your wayes traced with the eternal light of the Son of God which you hate and ſcof at, now doth your inſide appear, the ſheeps covering will no longer hide the ravening Wolfe; but he breaks forth in great rage and fury even <note place="margin">Matt. 7. 15, 16, 17.</note> ready to devour the Lambs of Chriſt, which walks Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently before you, who are inwardly ravening Wolves as your fruits makes you manifeſt, by which you are known, <note place="margin">Ezek. 34. i0.</note> as Chriſt Jeſus the light of the world hath foretold, which is now ſeen and fulfilled, glory be unto his eternal name for ever that your good words and fair ſpeeches will no longer hide you, but the children of light ſees you to be in the ſame ſteps of them, the Prophets Chriſt and the Apoſtles was ſent to cry againſt, which uſe your tongues <note place="margin">Matt. 23. Ier, 23. 30, 3i,</note> and ſay thus ſaith the Lord, when in the mean while you are perſecuting his Servants and ſlaying his Son, though <note place="margin">Matt. 7, 21.</note> you make a large profeſſion of him, and call him Lord and Maſter, but doth not the things which he commands but the things which his ſoule loathes.</p>
               <p>And thou <hi>Nathaniell Robinſon</hi> look upon thy congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea them which thou calls church members, which thou haſt ſowne unto, and ſee if there be any thing to be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168503:17"/>
reaped amongſt them but corruption, pride, luſt, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wantonneſſe, envying, ſtrife and debate, the moſt vaine faſhions and cuſtomes, of the world, which is to fade as the flower: And is not thy Vineyard full of this, can thou look upon them and not confeſſe thou art a ſhameleſſe Vinedreſſer, that can walk in this Vineyard without bluſhing? thy plants doth ſend forth an evil ſmell into the noſtrils of the Lord<hi>:</hi> Is not thy preaching vaine, and their faith vaine, and thy people yet in their ſins, and pleading for them for term of life? but if thou had ſtood <note place="margin">Ier. 23. 22.</note> in the councell of the Lord, and cauſed his people to have heard his word, then they ſhould have been turned from theſe abominations, which both thou and they are in, and pleading for, and perſecuting ſuch who teſtifies againſt them, and dare thou ſay that thou haſt brought them to witneſſe the firſt Principle of religion, or thinkeſt thou <note place="margin">Acts 26. 18. 1 Cor. 4 20.</note> the kingdome of Heaven ſtands in words, or the way to it is the way of uncleanneſſe, Pride, Envy &amp;c. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou and the reſt be not in ſuch wayes of darkneſſe <note place="margin">Iſa. 35. 8, 9, 10,</note> aforementioned yea or nay; if this be the vvay it is very broade, and many may go in thereat, and yet may profeſs as much of the Saints vvords as you can or doth, vvhile <note place="margin">Matt 7 13. Iohn 8. 44.</note> they themſelves are of their father the Devil as the Jevvs vvas, vvhoſe vvorks they did in perſecuting his Servants and ſtoneing him, and are not you doing the ſame? let the faithful Prophets of the Lord once ſpeak, and lend your <note place="margin">Deut. 18. 15.</note> eares a little unto him vvho vvill not flatter nor lye nor daube vvith untempred morter, for novv hath the Lord raiſed him according to his promiſe vvho ſpeaks vvith au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <note place="margin">Iohn 1. 45. Iohn 7. 37. 38.</note> and miniſters to the ſpirit in priſon, and all that vvill not harken unto him ſhall be cut off, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, and it ſhall be accompliſhed, and <note place="margin">Acts 3. 22.</note> unto him ſhall Kings bovv, and caſt dovvn their Crovvnes, Who vvill rule the Nations vvith a rod of Iron, and daſh them to peices as a Potters Veſſel, and novv vvoe <note place="margin">Iſa. 28 1.</note> unto the Crovvne of pride, that muſt be brought dovvn and laid in the duſt: And you that bear it the Lord vvill
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168503:17"/>
ſcatter in your Imaginations in vvhat form or profeſſion <note place="margin">Prov. 1. 5.</note> ſo ever you bee, though you be gathered together and hand joyn in hand, yet the vvicked ſhall not go unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <note place="margin">Matt. 3 8, 10.</note> novv this is ſad nevves to you, that are found vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Camp of the Lord, for it is novv fruits that he is now looking for, and righteouſneſſe that his ſoule delights in, and the heart that he requires; therefore hear this ye <note place="margin">Prov. 23. 16.</note> profeſſors of what ſort ſoever, who are out of the life and power of God, unto which every ſoule is to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1.</note> unto this power you are not brought, nor a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to it you do not know, but are under the power <note place="margin">Ephe. 2. 2.</note> of the Prince of the ayre which rules in you whereby ſome of you are led into pride, others into enmity, others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to abominable lyeing and falſe accuſeing the Innocent without a cauſe, now I know he who hath led you into theſe things will not let you confeſſe it, nor own that <note place="margin">Ezek. 23. 45. Dan 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. 1. Cor. 6. 2. i: Cor: 2. 16.</note> which condemns you ſecretly for it, but will bring Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for his own ends (as he did to Chriſt) and ſay I ſhould not judge; but I ſay the righteous loveth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the wicked cannot ſtand in it; and the Saints ſhall judge the world, and the Spiritual man judgeth all things, and he himſelfe is udged of no man, and your actions is to be condemned with the light, and troden upon as dirt in the ſtreets, with them who are in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God? Oh how the ſeed of God is oppreſſed amongſt you, that even the cry thereof hath entered into the ear of the Lord of Sabbaths, vvho is novv riſen to avenge his ovvn cauſe, and to plead vvith you who are in the fleſh, and are not only enemies to the ſeed of God in your ſelvs, but your rage abundantly apperrs towards any in whom it doth ariſe, to rule and guide them in the vvay that is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed holy; your abominations are increaſed, and your tranſgreſſions cannot be numbred, the Lord is weary vvith your ſacrifices, they are an abomination unto him; for no ſooner have you done that you call your ſacrifice, <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 12, 13, 14, 15. Prov. 15. 8.</note> if there be any in whom the ſeed of God is brought forth, that are ſent of him ro declare againſt your abominations,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168503:18"/>
before they can be ſuffered to ſpeak the words of truth in ſoberneſſe, you like doggs, and ſwine, Wolves, and Lions, <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 34, 35</note> do fall upon the Lambs of Chriſt, (who wrongeth no man neither can you lay any thing juſtly to their charge,) and pulls, and hails them out of your Aſſemblies even ready to <note place="margin">Luk. 19. 3.</note> take their bloud as <hi>Cain</hi> did, and caſts into priſon ſuch without any cauſe at all; are theſe a Company of ſheep, or of doggs, and Swine, yea, or nay? And is not this <hi>Cains</hi> way <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 5.</note> that you are found in, and is your ſacrifice more accepted of the Lord then his was? why are you ſo wroth &amp; envious? they that learn of Chriſt are meek, when they are ſmitten ſmites not again, or doe you ever read that any of them ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led out of their Aſſemblies, or perſecuted, or impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any? What adminiſtration do you live under? Anſwer in plainneſs, if you ſay you are Chriſtians, ſhew where ſuch actions were acted among Chriſtians; if not, confeſs it openly, and doe not play the Hypocrite; Read and ſee if your eies be not wholly blinded by the God of the World whom Yee worſhip and ſerve, who was an accuſer of the brethren from the beginning, and an envious man; Is not all out of order amongſt you, your children wild and rude in the evil communication which corrupts the good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 33.</note> brought up out of the fear of God, like wilde Colts, mocking, ſcoffing, ſtoneing, deriding, and ſcorning <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 4.</note> the Servants of the Lord in your Streets, ſo that thoſe that neither doth, nor ſpeaketh any thing to you that is evil, are daily by you abuſed both by words and actions as they paſs peaceably along the Streets; are not you that are Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents <note place="margin">Titus 2. 2, 3.</note> or Maſters to ſuch aſhamed of ſuch things (or doe you not delight in ſuch things,) your ſelves, and incourage your children and ſervants in it, What doe you think will be the end of theſe things, doe you not think the Lord ſcornes the ſcornfull, or what is it your malice is ſo much againſt?</p>
               <p>And again, is not your young men and maids uncivill, blaſpheming the name of the Lord, daily following youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <note place="margin">Titus 2. 4. 5, 6. Pſal. 119. 9.</note> pleaſures, living wantonly upon the earth, ſcoffing,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168503:18"/>
and ſcorning them that cannot partake with them in their filthy pleaſures, which will be bitter in the end, and are they not inventing how to make themſelves glorious in the ſight of the World, not remembring their Creator in the <note place="margin">Eccl. 12. 1.</note> daies of their youth, but following after pride and vanity which corrupts youth, and leads out of the Moderation, which they who fear the Lord are in, and are adorned with a meek and quiet ſpirit, which is of great price in the ſight of God. And doth not your Women array themſelves in coſtly apparell, in gold and pearle, contrary to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 9. 10. 1 Pet: 3. 2, 3, 4.</note> command, and doe not they goe in hoods, and vailes, ſcarfes, and rings, and changable Suits of Apparell, and walking with ſtretched out necks, and wanton eies, making <note place="margin">Iſa: 3. 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26.</note> a mincing as they goe, and a tinkling with their feet; and their broadered hair; that they can ſcarce tell how to goe they are ſo proud, and puft up in the luſt of the Fleſh, even ſuch (if not worſe) as the Lord ſent his plagues, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon. Read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26.</p>
               <p>Therefore hear this all you that are found in this path, the Lord will take away your bravery, and inſtead thereof he will cover you with contempt, and he will bring down the haughtineſs of man and woman, and will lay your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <note place="margin">Iſa: 2. 11, 12, 13, 17. Iſa: 10. 33.</note> in the duſt; and ſcatter you as chaff is ſcattered with the Wind, becauſe you have caſt his righteous Law behind your backs, and hath walked deſpightfully againſt the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Grace; Who hath been warned like unto you? hath not the Lord ſent his Servants earlie and late to forewarn You of the Judgement that he hath intended againſt You becauſe of Your manie tranſgreſſions; whereby You daily provoke him to anger; even to ſweep You all awaie with the beſome of deſtruction?</p>
               <p>And have not You executed Your cruelty upon his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers in mocking, ſcoffing, ſpitting upon, hailing to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <note place="margin">Math: 23. 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39.</note> them that have been ſent in tender love unto your Souls, to call You to Repentance, and to ſeek the Lord while he may be found: but You may ſay, You doe not this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168503:19"/>
to the ſervants of Chriſt, but to Vagabonds and Wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Deluders, and Deceivers, and the Ringleaders of the Sect of the Quakers, (as You in ſcorn calls them) which is every where ſpoken againſt, and hailed out of the <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues,</hi> and perſecuted, and caſt into priſon, but all this while cannot ſee Your ſelves as blind as Your Forefathers the Perſecutors was, and as ignorant of God, and his works as <hi>Cain</hi> the Vagabond was, vvho vvas in Envie as you are, though he builded the firſt Cittie to make bimſelf an habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 12.</note> God called him a Vagabond, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 12. but he did not call his Son a Vagabond, vvho had not vvhereon to lay his head, nor his Son did not call them vvhich vvent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in Sheep skins, and goat skins, and had no certain <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 35, 36, 37, 38, 39 40.</note> dvvelling place, he did not call ſuch Vagabonds, vvho had a habitation vvhere neither <hi>Cain</hi> nor any of his ſtock hath, but you are the Vagabonds rightly named vvho are in envie and vvrath, vvho hath great habitations in the earth as he had, but are driven out from the preſence of the Lord into pride and highmindedneſs, and into the Earth, and its pleaſure, and treaſure, laying up treaſure there, but are ignorant of the true treaſure vvhich they have in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 7.</note> veſſels vvhich vvander up and dovvn, and are made a prey upon by you, vvho are in <hi>Cains</hi> vvay, and in God hath not an habitation, but are vvandering ſtarres, vvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering <note place="margin">Iſa: 59. 15.</note> up and dovvn in the Element of your imaginations, out of one faſhion and vanitie of the World into another; and here are you ſcattered upon the mountains of Pride and high mindedneſs, in the clouds of darkneſs, and ſtops your eares at the true Shepheards voice, vvho would gather you off from the barren mountains into the lovv vallies, to feed among his Lambs, and to drink of the freſh foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of living Water, but this You loath, and vvill not hear of, but loves to vvallovv vvith the Svvine in the filth, and mire, therefore vvill Your condemnation be juſt, and the Lord vvill be clear of Your blood.</p>
               <p>Again, is not the harmleſs and innocent children of the Lord vvhom he hath placed his Name in, and hath ſet as <note place="margin">Phill. 2. i5.</note>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:168503:19"/>
Witneſſes againſt you, as he did <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom;</hi> whom you have nothing juſtly to lay to their charge, are not ſuch by <note place="margin">1 Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> you abuſed as <hi>Lot</hi> was, ſcoffed and ſcorned at, ſtoned in the Streets and ſpitted upon, who cannot goe with you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame exceſs of riot, doe you think the Lord doth <note place="margin">1 Pet: 4. 4.</note> not take notice of this? Yea, ſurely one day ye ſhall know that it had been better for you that a milſtone had been hanged about your necks, and you caſt into the midſt of <note place="margin">John 15. 19.</note> the ſea, then to offend one of the leaſt of his, who is the good Shepherd, but becauſe Judgement is not executed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Math: 18. 6. Eccl: 8. 11.</note> you ſpeedily, therefore are your hearts bent in you to doe wickedly; but this know, that there is a Witneſs in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of your conſciences, that takes notice of all your waies and actings; therefore once more I warn you from the Lord to repent and turn unto the Lord, and put off your bravery of your tinkling ornaments, and put on ſackcloth, and ſit down in the duſt, if ſo be you may be hid in the day of the fierce indignation of the Lord, and ceaſe to doe evil, and learn to doe well, leſt the overflowing ſcourge of the Lord ſweep you all away, for his ſword is <note place="margin">Iſa. i. 16, 17.</note> drawn, and his bow bent, and his arrowes are made very ſharp, and will fall grievouſly upon the head of the wicked <note place="margin">Amos 5. 14, 15, 16.</note> and how can you eſcape when he appears, who will plead with you by his Sword, and by Fire, and will render to every man according to his works, without <note place="margin">Math. 16. 27.</note> reſpect of perſons, and then ſhall you all know that you had warning in your life time, by them which you hated and perſecuted; ſcoffed and ſcorned; ſo while you have time prize it, and ſleight not the day of your Viſitation, nor the mercie of the Lord to your Souls, leaſt you be ſhut out among the Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers into utter darkneſs, where is weeping, wailing, <note place="margin">Math. 8. 12.</note> and gnaſhing of teeth for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:168503:20"/>
I charge you as you will anſwer it to the Lord, ſearch theſe Scriptures out, which are quoted, and read them in the fear of God; and try your teachers, and your fruits, whether they be according to them which ſpoke forth Scriptures, Yea, or Nay, for every tree is known by his fruits, and ſo are the falſe prophets from the true, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7, 20.</p>
               <p>Written by me whom you greatly hate, becauſe I am ſent to bear teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt your abominations, and by you am I called a Quaker, but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the tender mercy of the Lord, am I made partaker of the Divine nature, <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 4.</note> and onely known to the world by the name of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ambroſe Rigge.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:168503:20"/>
               <p>ANd now Oh ye Rulers of the earth, the word of the Lord is to you; who hath gotten the Seat of <hi>Moſes</hi> the Servant of the Lord; you who are called Judges, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, or Head Officers of what kind or ſort ſoever; And doth pretend that you are Gods Miniſters to lay the ſword upon the tranſgreſſors, and to be a praiſe unto them that doth well, according as the Lord hath appointed his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to be, now if you profeſs the Scriptures to be your rule and the Chriſtian Magiſtrates to be your example, which is recorded in the Scriptures; Let us now reaſon together in meekneſs, and trie your fruits whether they be according to the Magiſtrates in the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, and Apoſtles, Yea or Nay? I ſpeak of them who were Gods Miniſters indeed, and did not bear their Sword in vain, but was a terror to evil doers, and a praiſe to them that did well, according as God had ordained them.</p>
               <p>Firſt Conſider, are you ſuch as <hi>Moſes</hi> chuſed in his daies to be Rulers over the people, even men fearing God and men of truth, hating Covetouſneſs, as you may read, <hi>Exod,</hi> 18. the 21, 22, 23, 24, 25.</p>
               <p>Again, are you ſuch as God commanded his Miniſters to be in the daies of <hi>Moſe,</hi> who commanded them to doe no unrighteouſneſs in Judgment, nor to reſpect the perſon of the poor, nor honour the perſon of the mighty, as you may read, <hi>Levi.</hi> 19. 15.</p>
               <p>Again, are you ſuch as <hi>Moſes</hi> charged his to be, who was to judge righteouſly between every man and his brother, and the Stranger that was with him; and were nor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect perſons in Judgement, but to hear the ſmall as well as the great, as you may ſee, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1. 16, 17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16. 18, 19.</p>
               <p>Again, are you ſuch as <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> the King ſet over the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:168503:21"/>
people, who doth not judge for man but for the Lord, and is the fear of God upon you, with whom there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons or taking of gifts, as you may read 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 19. 4. 5, 6, 7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 23. 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 14. 14. Now let but the witneſs of God in you all ſpeak, and it will plainly tell you whether you, and your Judgment be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them and theirs, yea, or nay.</p>
               <p>And whatſoever cauſe came before them between blood and blood, and between Law and Commandement, thus were they to doe in the fear of God faithfully, and with a perfect heart, they were even to warn them not to treſpaſs againſt the Lord, leaſt wrath came upon them, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 9, 10. Is this ſo among you oh ye Rulers of <hi>England</hi> of what degree ſoever, would not you even cauſe them to treſpaſs againſt the Lord that dare not, in perſecuting and impriſoning them that dare not break his commands?</p>
               <p>Again, are you ſuch as doth execute the Judgment of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, and widdows, and loveth the Stranger in giving him food and raiment, as you may read, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. 17, 18, 19. or are you not ſuch as daily ſeeks to enſnare and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Strangers under the name of wanderers, and inſtead of giving of them food and raiment (according to the command of God,) doth caſt them into priſon, and whip, ſtock, and ſtone them, yea, or nay? as you have done many of the ſervants of the living God within this few years, who by faith hath (according to the command of God,) left their countrie, and fathers houſe, and are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Strangers and pilgrims in the earth, having in it no certain dwelling place, as it was with the holy men of God in former ages: as you may ſee, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 36, 37, 38. 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2. 21.</p>
               <p>Again, are you ſuch as <hi>David</hi> was, whom the God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ſet to rule over the people, being a juſt man, and ruling in the fear of God 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:168503:21"/>
Again; are you ſuch as God commanded the Princes of Iſrael to be, who ſaid let it ſuffice you, O ye Princes of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, remove violence, and ſpoile and execute Judgement, and Juſtice, and take away your exactions from my people, as you may read, <hi>Exek.</hi> 45. 9. or are not you ſuch as uſe violence to them that cannot bend to your pride and luſt, and ſend out your Warrants to ſpoil the goods of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent who cannot for conſcience ſake uphold that which they know and ſee the hand of the Lord is turned againſt? here you are found not to be ſuch as removs violence &amp; ſpoil, but are the defenders &amp; warrants of ſuch who by violence &amp; ſpoil, doth daily oppreſs the poor, fatherleſs, and widows<hi>:</hi> And as for taking away your exactions from the people of God, that you are far enough from, for you caſts them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to priſon, and then adds affliction to their bonds, in ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their goods; and binds heavie burthens upon them which are grievous to be born, which you your ſelves will not touch with one of your fingers; now whether this be not as far contrary to them in former ages as light is from darkneſs let any that fears the Lord judge.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, are you ſuch as was in the daies of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles whom he commanded the children of God to be ſubject unto; who ſtood in the power of God, and was a terror to evil doers, and a praiſe to them that did well, and did not bear their ſwords in vain, but was miniſters of God to execute wrath upon them that did evil; unto ſuch they was to be ſubject not onely for wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake, as you may read, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p>Again, ſearch and trie whether you and your ordinances be ſuch as the Apoſtle <hi>Pete</hi> commanded the Saints to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto for the Lords ſake, whether it was to the King as Supream, or unto Governors as unto them that was ſent by him, for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that doe well, as you may read, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2. 13, 14. (marke) they was to ſubmit to every ordinance of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:168503:22"/>
man for the Lords ſake, which was for the puniſhment of evil doers, But he did not command them to ſubmit to ſuch ordinances of men as was for the puniſhment of ſuch as obeyed the command of God; now let the witneſſe of God in you all, ſearch you, and ſee whether you be ſuch Judges, Juſtices and Rulers as is aforementioned, yea or nay? who was men fearing God, and did not reſpect the perſon of the poor, nor honour the perſon of the mightie, and was not to take gifts; Now if you be ſuch, he that is not ſubject to you reſiſteth the ordinance of God. But if you be found in the ſteps of them who were oppreſſors of Gods people, that when your pride is not bowed unto, doth in your rage and furie perſecute, and caſt into priſon the innocent chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Lord, contrarie both to the law of God, and man; I ſay they that reſiſts this power, doth not reſiſt the ordinance of God, for ſuch a power was never ordained of God, but ſet up in the corrupt Wills of men; therefore they that comes to be turned from darkneſſe to the light, and from the power of Satan unto the power of God, (which is the higher power which every ſoul is to be ſubject unto) doth rather chuſe to ſuffer by that power then to be ſubject unto ill, as you may read <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 14, 15, 16, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26.</p>
               <p>And now we ſhall come to ſearch into the actions, and fruites of the Heatheniſh Kings and Rulers recorded in the Scripture of truth, who were perſecuters of the people of God, and weigh their actions with yours, who are called Chriſtian Magiſtrates in this Nation of <hi>England,</hi> and ſee whether doth over-ballance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:168503:22"/>
               <head>So theſe are left as Queries to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by any of you.</head>
               <p n="1">1. VVHether <hi>Pharoah</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> who oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the children of God, might not have pleaded, as well as you, That they were to be ſubject to his command, and bow down to his power, yea or nay? who ſaid, <hi>Come let us deal wiſely with them, leſt they multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and grow ſtronger then we, that when there fall out any war, they become our enemies, and fight againſt us;</hi> and he uſed cruel rigor unto them, and laid great burthens upon them, as you may read <hi>Exod.</hi> the firſt chap. Now whether or no is not this your Wiſdom now, To uſe all your power and ſtrength to oppreſs the people of God now by cruel bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and rigor, and when your power is not ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, doth join together, and take counſel to make cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Laws againſt them, whereby to bring them into bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and make them ſerve you as Bond-ſlaves, which you cannot read that <hi>Pharoah</hi> did? So whether your cruelty doth not exceed his, yea or nay, let that in all your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences judge.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether this power that <hi>Pharoah</hi> ruled in, was the power of God, yea or nay? If yea, Why did the Lord with an high hand and an outſtretched arm, deliver his children from him and his power, and overthrow him, and his Chariots and Horſemen, in the midſt of the Sea? as you may read <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28. If nay, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your power be not the ſame now, in oppreſſing the innocent children of God now, whom he hath appointed to offer a ſacrifice to him in righteouſneſs? And whether ever any that ſtood in the power of God, and was guided by the Spirit of God, was ever perſecutors, yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:168503:23"/>
3. Where did ever <hi>Pharoah</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt</hi> fine or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon any of the people of the Lord for ſuch a ſmall thing as not for putting off their Hats, as many of you have done? Or whether he did oppreſs the people of God ſo many waies as you have done within theſe late Years, yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Where did ever <hi>Moſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> who was a true and faithful Judge over all Iſrael, fine or impriſon any that came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him for not putting off their Hats? Shew one exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple either among the Chriſtian Magiſtrates throughout the Scriptures, or among the Heatheniſh Rulers in former ages and if you cannot find one example among either of them, then confeſs your ſelves to be grown higher in pride and ambition then the perſecutors in former ages.</p>
               <p n="5">5 VVhether there be anie tranſgreſſion where there is no Law? If you ſay Yea; ſhew how, or wherein; If Nay, then whether do not you perſecute and impriſon them that are no tranſgreſſors for not putting off their Hats, when there is neither Law of God, nor man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. VVhere did <hi>Balaak</hi> King of the <hi>Moabites,</hi> whoſe enmitie was againſt the people of God, whom God had delivered from under the hand of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> as you may read <hi>Numb.</hi> 22. 4, 5, 6. yet ſhew where he perſecuted or impriſoned ſo many of them as you have done of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Lord, who are in deriſion called <hi>Quakers,</hi> in the Nation of <hi>England,</hi> without any juſtcauſe? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the power was not in him to do it, aswell as you, yea or nay.</p>
               <p n="7">7. VVhether <hi>Haman</hi> (who was full of wrath when <hi>Mordecai</hi> could not bow unto him as others did) was in the power of God, or in the pride of his heart, who made a Gallows to hang <hi>Mordecai</hi> on, becauſe he croſſed his luſt? as you may read <hi>Eſth.</hi> 5. Now whether you who are full of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:168503:23"/>
rage and fury when the people of God cannot bow down to your pride and luſt, be not in the ſame ſteps, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>Therefore conſider what was the end of <hi>Haman,</hi> read <hi>Eſth.</hi> 7. 9, 10.</p>
               <p n="8">8. VVhether <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> (who was a heatheniſh King) ſtood in the power of God, when he commanded to bind he three children of God, and caſt them into the fiery Fornace becauſe they could not bow to his will, as you may read <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. the whole chapter? Now you that ſay all power is of God, and therefore ought to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whether did <hi>Shadrak, Meſhek,</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> well in reſiſting this power, and chooſing rather to ſuffer under it, then obey it, yea or nay? as you may ſee <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 16, 17, 18. So you who commands the people of God to bow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which in conſcience to the Lord they cannot, are not you full of rage and fury, and commands them to be caſt into priſon without Bail or Mainpriſe, and makes their affliction ſeven-fold worſe then it uſed to be to others who were offenders? So what this Power and command differs from <hi>Nebuchadnezzars,</hi> let that in all your conſciences judge,</p>
               <p n="9">9. VVhether <hi>Darius</hi> the King ſtood in the power of God when he commanded <hi>Daniel</hi> to be caſt into the Den of Lyons for praying to the true God? as you may read <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 16. If you ſay Yea; VVhether did <hi>Daniel</hi> well, yea or nay, in not regarding the King, nor the Decree that he had ſigned? <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 13. If Nay; VVhether you ſtand not in the ſame power now, who caſts into Dens and Holes the children of the Lord, whoſe prayers he hears, becauſe they cannot bow down to any but to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="10">10. VVhether <hi>Herod</hi> who impriſoned <hi>Peter</hi> the ſervant
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:168503:24"/>
of God, was in the power of God, yea or nay? as you may read <hi>Act.</hi> 12. 3. 4. If you ſay Yea, then why did God ſend his Angel, and deliver <hi>Peter</hi> from him, and ſmite <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> that he was eaten with VVorms? as you may read <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 12. 7, 8, &amp; 23. If you ſay Nay, Then all power is not of God by your own confeſſion, but the Devil keeps many under his power, to act his will upon the children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God.</p>
               <p n="11">11. VVhether King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> or <hi>Feſtus,</hi> or <hi>Foelix,</hi> who had as much power to execute their wills upon the ſervants of God as you have now, yet ſhew wherein they acted half ſo much rigor upon the ſervants of Chriſt, as many of you have acted? Therefore now conſider your ſtate, and weigh your actions and fruits; and in this your day I warn you all, high and low, to mind the things that belongs to your peace before they be hid from your eyes, and you be ſhut up in utter darkneſs; for the Spirit of the Lord will not alwaies ſtrive vvith you as it hath done. Therefore be wiſe now ye Kings, and be inſtructed ye Judges and Rulers of the Earth; ſerve the Lord with fear, and rejoice before him with trembling; kiſs the Son leſt he be angry, and you periſh from the way; for if his VVrath be kindled a little, bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him: And ceaſe perſecuting the inocent, vvho neither vvrongeth you, nor any man; and conſider the end of the perſecutors in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages, <hi>Pharoah</hi> the oppreſſor of Gods people vvas drovvned in the depth of the Sea, as you may ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. 27, 28. <hi>Haman</hi> vvas hanged on the Gallovvs that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for <hi>Mordecai,</hi> read <hi>Eſth.</hi> 7 9, 10. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> his Kingdom vvas rent from him, and his dvvelling vvas vvith the Beaſts of the field, and did eat graſſe as the Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en: Read <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 32, 33.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Darius</hi> was made to repent, and confeſs to the truth, That it vvas the true God that <hi>Daniel</hi> ſerved, vvhom he perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as you may read <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 26, 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:168503:24"/>
                  <hi>Herod</hi> vvas eaten vvith VVorms vvho priſoned and perſecuted the ſervants of God as you may read, <hi>Acts</hi> 12. 23. Theſe things I vvrite unto you that you may ſee the juſt judgements of the Lord upon the perſecutors of his in former ages; not that I deſire in the leaſt ſuch things to come upon you, but that vvhile you have time, to priſe it, and return to the Lord, if ſo be you may be hid in the day of his fierce vvrath. So thus far am I clear of all your blood, vvho am knovvn in <hi>England</hi> by the Name of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ambroſe Rigge.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
